Hi Warren.
This is Fabric Academy 2024 25th.
This is, um, tutorial on open source circular fashion
week number three, and I'll start sharing my screen.
Um, begin, um, with the pattern construction, this is
what I am aiming to do today with you
so we can start working in the real size.
Uh, how can interlock pieces together, how we can start
designing patterns and modules.
Uh, also with a little bit of math, uh, symmetries
and relationships between the parts of the model.
So, um, I'm gonna, uh, this is fusion.
Um, I'm gonna create a new file so we can start over.
And this is how basically the interface appears.
Um, the first thing, um, to do here, of course,
is, uh, going to the top few.
Uh, be sure you can see correctly.
Um, here, there is a kind of a menu
with folders that are clickable.
Be sure the units is millimeters.
If it's not, you can double click onto the icon, change it.
I recommend you to use millimeters and not centimeters
'cause you're dealing, um, this during this week
with very tiny, um,
measurement, uh, with small numbers.
Uh, and also be sure here at the very end,
there is the icon for the timeline.
So whatever you do, um, on the software on this
board is gonna be recorded at the end.
That means that you can always go back to previous command,
admitting people and everything will be,
uh, recorded for you here.
So, um, I always recommend you
to use the mouse if you also want to navigate, uh,
different, uh, uh, views of your file.
Um, here at the top right, there is a house.
So you can always relocate back, um,
your design at the center of the grid,
or, uh, click on the different phases of the cube here.
Um, our design is gonna be flat.
It's gonna be printed, so we always work on the top face.
Be sure you are gonna face, uh, what you see here.
And of course you have commands that are pretty common
to different software like the pan.
So you can always, um, also navigate, uh, with the mouse,
um, back and forth.
You have a zoom
and you have something very useful
that is gonna be, um, fit.
I have six fit two windows,
so you can always er your pattern,
um, to begin with.
So what I was showing early is what I'm aiming to do.
And, and this is very, very, uh, first minutes.
It will not take a while.
Um, fusion is very intuitive software, uh,
very different from Rhino,
but still you can, you might be able to recognize,
uh, similar tools.
Um, so as we said, we are here on the top face
and we begin creating, uh, what Fusion calls a sketch.
So our pattern will be a vector, will be a sketch.
And in order to create the first command,
we just click on on the top icon you see here.
So create sketch one, click here one, click on the board,
and be sure you see a sketch palette here,
a sketch icon at the very bottom of your software
and different tools happening here.
Uh, you should also be able to see a green button
that says Finish sketch.
So now you're outside the sketch.
In order to modify your pattern, your module,
you must enter inside the sketch.
So double click you're in, double click or,
or click on the button, the green button to go out.
So now that we're here, we can create, uh, a module
and we have, uh, great choice front of us.
Usually everything, uh, starts with basic shapes.
Uh, you can pick a circle, you can pick a rectangle.
Um, if you're real beginning with the software,
you can follow me.
Um, if you're experienced,
you can just pick any shape you want and create your own.
Um, yesterday was showing the circles as a first approach.
So I'm gonna replicate that
and I'm gonna go click under create
and select a circle from the center.
There are many options for different polygons
that you can insert in your design.
Uh, you can only choose if you want your circle
to start from the origin from the center rather than 2.3
points and so on.
So I'm gonna just use the circle
and, uh, I'm just clicking on the command.
And in order to position it somewhere on the plane here,
I must click and specify the point I want it to be.
Um, usually you can use the grid that you see here.
You have a origin and two access.
So, um, for example, you can click in the middle of the grid
and specify that it's gonna be also your center.
So one click and, uh, second click to release.
You can only press, uh, escape from the keyboard
to remove the selection
and select it, uh, with a mouse with a pointer.
It should be, um, it should be blue.
Um, so we just picked a circle.
We don't know, uh, the dimension.
It was just random fusion as, um, a great way to deal
with, uh, dimensions.
There is under create.
Most of the commands you're gonna find useful, uh,
for this week will be actually here, uh,
under create or modify.
So under create or uh, d for the people who refer
to your shortcuts in the keyboard, you can create,
you can use, um, sketch dimension
and click on the edge of the circle of your polygon
and click, um, to be able to insert a number.
This, as you can see here, is gonna be millimeters.
So for example, you can select everything
and write, uh, five centimeters.
If you want your circle to be, um, smaller,
you can just double click anytime.
And the, um, size
of your module will be adopted accordingly.
Um, so let's say 50 was okay.
Uh, you can find the command here as a shortcut
or again here in sketch dimensions.
Um, so this is our first shape.
Of course, you can move the dimension, whatever you want.
I suggest you to keep it outside
to leave the, uh, sketch clean.
Um, and we can try to add some cuts like so yesterday,
some slots, um, to create a female
and a male to be able to interlock between each other.
Um, so basically gonna add
this kind of connections.
We are gonna start with the female.
This is a square, but follows the same exact process.
So how do we create these parts
for the other male part
to be interlocked and connected together?
Um, the correct way is of course, uh,
user agreed to use references.
What you can use fusion is, for example, lines.
Uh, of course there are count countless ways to do, uh,
to create a pattern to do what I'm going to show now.
Uh, a convenient way is to use the line
that you can also find here, or l in the keyboard.
And for example, um, create a reference.
So from the center of your polygon to, um, all the way up,
keeping straight, uh, you can use escape
to remove the command or click somewhere else.
Okay, I'll do it again.
So I just want to create an access basically.
And I'm gonna take the line, click from the center.
If you're not sure what you're clicking, you should be able
to see a pointer like, uh, across
and the center of your board of your,
your module highlighted.
So place the first point
and place the second, uh, whatever you see here
before confirming.
If you see the, um, the square, a blue square means that,
uh, you are actually perpendicular or vertical
or horizontal.
You don't have to hold shift.
Fusion is, uh, say smart enough to understand, uh,
let you know that you are going exactly straight.
Um, when you're done, you see this icon, you can confirm
and your line is being created.
Um, you should be able
to see this catch palette.
You can, uh, if it's, um, collapsed, you can just click
and expand the different command.
Uh, this is useful if you want, uh, to give relationships
to, um, different lines and parts of the module.
But also, for example, you can specify that this
line is not part of the construction
and is actually, um, an access.
So you should be able to see it.
Uh, with dotted lines, we're just creating a reference.
This is useful because if I want to create this kind
of slots, I can just use, uh, I don't have to create all
of them, uh, separated, but I can just create one
and use, uh, something called the circular pattern
to create an array of the same line.
So, for example, I can proceed to create the first lot
and uh, I have plenty also commands here to use.
I can just go again with the line.
I can place it anywhere, confirm the selection,
click on the, uh, dimension
or here sketch dimension, select the line
and just put a number.
So for example, I want this to be, uh,
10 millimeters, one centimeter.
And as you can see here, I just assigned the value
to the line and I'm actually able to move it anywhere else.
So I want it to be exactly at a specific, for example,
um, distance between the center.
So I can always, uh, let's say lock it down
with the dimension command as well
and specify two different points.
So I can go back to the sketch dimension either here again
or down and click two different points.
And say, for example, this gonna be,
um, two centimeters.
Now I'm able to move this way back and forth.
But, uh, since we created Anxi
before, the aim was to put, uh,
to center line, the line to the module.
So, uh, you can see here on top there is an array
of constraints and these are just, uh, icons
that you can select in order to apply a constraint,
a relationship between, again, different lines
and different parts of the modules.
So what I want to lock down is this line
and put it in the middle, um, of the axis here.
So I'm gonna select the line holding, shift the axis,
and I'm gonna choose between the constraints.
Uh, midpoint, uh, if you zoom in a little bit,
you see that there is an icon.
Um, there's a triangle, identifies the midpoint.
So now I'm not able to move, uh, my line
in any direction between,
because it's been, uh, locked down here.
So it's exactly where I want it to be.
I can of course update the measurement
and now we can see that it was, uh, equally both size.
I can even put, uh, 40,
I can do z.
Uh, let's skip it. 10.
And again, here I can only specify
the distance between the center.
Um, and the point, I can put 25
and clearly it's gonna be outside of the module
10 is gonna be furthermore inside,
but I think 20 was a good number to start with.
So once I did this, I can select my line
and actually create a pattern.
Of course, I could actually mirror it since I have an, uh,
an access here, I could actually use the access of the grid.
But I think, uh, in this case,
the circular pattern is just more convenient.
So the moment I just select the line, I'll do it again.
And I'm going to choose the command circular pattern.
This popup will come,
it shows one selected because I selected the line first.
It can always, um, delete the selection
and choose the object you want to pattern.
And a center, the center point, I can use the one
of the grid, or in this case the circle
and create a pattern.
So how many slots I want to be present in my module.
And of course, uh, I think you got now the logic of fusion.
So even though I specify I want to
before, I can always go back and update time.
The number, so from four i one, six
rate, or just three.
And this is the icon of the pattern of the circular pattern.
So let's say four.
And basically this can just be considered a module.
If I'm happy with what I did, I can just finish this sketch.
And, uh, of course, for example, exported as the xf
or nesting to put into another software.
If I want to modify this design, again, I just double click
again, either here on my sketch
or down in the timeline here.
If I actually double click on the name,
I can call it circle female.
Double click to enter the selection.
And if I don't want any line,
'cause I have some access, for example, I can just decide
to trim all the lines.
I don't need to be in the design.
Uh, the dimensions, they don't really matter.
They will not appear in the final DXF.
Uh, the moment you specify different relationships
between the parts, uh, it's always, uh, a good practice
to keep the access at any construction lines you have.
Just, uh, if you export the final, you can, uh, for example,
me, I I would leave everything here, constructed infusion
and then moving, for example,
onto illustrator to handle battery.
The nesting part, I will just get rid of the line, uh,
before parting the whole circles.
Um, I dunno if it was clear. Uh, there is question on this.
So there is something, I was too fast
'cause I would like to create the other part,
but if you have question about it, you can unmute
and uh, let me know.
Okay, I can consider it was quite clear.
So we have our female,
we can create the second one for interlocking.
Again, you have plenty of options.
Uh, one of those is, uh, again, you go back to the,
to the same sketch for example, you can select everything
and you can copy paste it,
Contra C, contra V,
or if you press, um,
removing, you're actually able to create a copy
from the option here and you can move it wherever you want.
So now this is a copy
and both of the designs, um,
shouldn't be related to each other.
So if I change the first one, the second, uh,
design I have, it's like independent.
So I can use the first circle I made
to be my female and this new one for the male part.
So how we can, um, in a matter
of seconds also create this, uh, uh, parts
that are gonna be designed to go inside
and lock my shape perfectly.
Again, you have plenty of options.
Um, a general rule, uh, when we release a cut fabric
and redesign connection, for example, for new premium,
but also felt is to keep, um,
the same tolerance and let's say the same measurements.
So, um, I can use the line
and keep this force lots I design in a designed
earlier as referenced.
So this means that if you look
at the male part, the distance between this kind of arrow
is the same as this slot I created before.
If the females lot is bigger than the male part,
basically your connection is not gonna hold.
That means that the male part should be equal
or a little bit bigger than the female.
So, uh, in order to create this part, I can take the line
for example and just select
place the first point here
all the way to the circle.
And this is the line I created.
Of course I could, now that I have an axis mirror it,
uh, all the commands are basically here.
So under create I select mirror.
I have a mirror line that I can use
and I can already see, um,
before confirming the selection that I have a preview.
So again, I select the mirror
line and I confirm.
So now you see more icons.
These are the icons that specify
that the mirror command has been applied.
Uh, if these amounts of icons are bothering you,
you can just, uh, um, go back
and create manually with the line
The second one.
But the moment you want to specify relationships
between all the parties, a good practice to use, uh,
to design ones and use all the different commands to pattern
to create array, uh, meter and so on.
So I'm gonna do it again.
I take the line from this point to the circle.
Um, if you press base bar in the keyboard,
you actually have access to the previous command
or you can find all them here
and um, still with the mirror.
So this line, the mirror line here,
and I have them created.
Uh, again, I said if we don't want the construction lines,
um, to be part of the design, for example, a females lot,
we can just get rid of them.
We trim or delete, we keep the access
because we use for the mirror.
And now we have these two lines
that we can pattern, for example.
So we have the references here, we can do, um,
basically go back to the same command.
So create a circular pattern, a standard point.
And again, this 3, 4, 6,
since we have four slots, um, designed earlier for the fema,
we're gonna create also for repetitions here.
And this is basically how um, your models will be connected.
You can always, um, select everything, click,
move, and see how your design is gonna overlap.
So for example, if you move both of them onto illustrator,
you select onto to different colors, you apply some opacity,
you're actually able to already preview, add, intersect
before printing,
uh, for the nesting part of course.
So you can do this infusion,
you can even move them onto another layer onto,
onto another sketch.
Uh, but I would like to show some illustrator integration
of different software.
Then I can just do finish the sketch.
Of course I can save it either on the cloud
or on on my laptop.
These are not female, these are female male.
Now, uh,
five centimeters and I can just do save as the itself.
And yeah, here I have two access.
Well basically if I want, I can just get rid
of them if this is my final pattern.
So I can double click again, uh, enter the sketch mode
and just stream the axis.
Otherwise I have to train the administrator.
Um,
um, is there any questions so far?
Okay, no, uh, we can continue.
Um, okay, I hope, uh, you can see, um, illustrator here.
So basically we can, uh, um, create a new document.
If you know in advance, um,
the dimensions of your textile piece
or the bed of the laser that you can directly, uh,
use the dimensions, um, you have at your hand.
You can change 'em from here.
Be sure also you are dealing with millimeters.
You can specify the number of art boards.
Uh, be sure the color mode set up is LGB
and um, you're ready to go.
Of course you can always change your
canvas dimensions later on.
And this is the icon illustrator to do that
we saw a little bit last time.
Also, uh, how illustrator works. Um, it handle vectors.
So, um, here is the, one of the best software,
let's say also very intuitive to, uh,
create nesting, but also a pattern.
You don't have to use fusion, you can use rhino
or any other software you're comfortable with.
I think an illustrator is very easy to create, uh,
um, symmetries to create pattern as well.
It just a little bit more tricky to work in real size.
Uh, you don't have plenty of options
to establish relationships in the parts of the modules,
but of course also you have, um, rulers
if you do not see them, uh, like me in this case,
you can enable from view
and you can find the command here
or command r ctrl r keyboard
and show this, uh, magnetic rules
that you can just drag and drop it anywhere
and delete if you don't need anymore.
So what are
or trying to do here is to, uh,
organize the models altogether.
I can import from file, for example,
and the circles that we just created
or I can just open them,
um,
or convenient.
Uh, drag and wrap inside.
I had the previous one. Okay,
circle, uh, the moment to import
or your open your file.
Also be sure its says original size and the scale.
One unit correspond to one millimeter inside.
So this is how uh, your design should be appearing.
Be sure every time you change software
there is no double line.
So the moment you click on one line sheet,
see only one moving.
And here again, a circle and not space between each other.
The first thing to do usually is to create groups.
So you can move one element, um,
with all the different lines together.
To do so, you just select all the lines you want
to be part of the group.
And then you can say in the keyboard, CTL G,
command G or you should be able to see
this bar a little bit down that says group or ungroup.
So you should be able to move everything in one go.
Uh, fusion also has this, um, candle snaps.
So you can always see when the two shapes are aligned
between each other when they should point this kind
of magnetic rules,
or, uh, if you want to be sure these two shapes are aligned,
you can select for example, uh, there like this, let's say
you can select both of them
and use, uh, one of the alignment tool
that you see on top here.
So example in this case would be perfectly center aligned
in this case of course will be overlapped and so on.
Again here you can choose if you want them to be aligned
to selection or to the board.
That means in this case here on top
of your cameras, uh,
let's say they're fine like this center aligned.
So I can also move them together because I select them both.
And in order to laser cut this, I need to set up,
for example, the color we say we are in RGB mode.
It's also written here if you're not sure.
So on top of your um, file, it's written, uh,
the color space, double click on the color.
Be sure to enable only web colors
and find the red 2 55, 0 0.
You should also be able to see the color on top
and also multiple other locations here on the board.
Of course, it's not mandatory to use red.
You can use any color you want as long
as it is, uh, RGB.
Um, the other parameter to set up is the stroke.
So as we were saying, usually the resolution
of delays is 0.01 millimeters
or in some software you can use the option hairline
and it's normal that your line becomes very, very thin.
So just zoom in and be sure, um, your file is still here
or if you press common Y on your keyboard,
you're actually able to see the x-ray of your design.
You can move it very close to the board.
And uh, we have a male and the female here.
We can for example, start partnering, uh,
copying the circles all over.
Uh, again, there are so many commands here to do
that we can, uh, for example, select both of them
and uh, was showing this when also two weeks ago.
So if you press on your keyboard, uh, alt
or option on the Mac, you should be able to see this cloning
icon next to the pointer.
And you can just, uh,
or shift drag it
Central aligned until you meet, uh, the point
of the other circles.
And then if you press command D should be able
to replicate this one, um, as much
as you want onto it.
Also, uh, you undo all the steps.
So again, you can select both of them.
You can of course copy paste them,
but like this, it's much faster.
So option in the keyboard, you should be able
to see this icon.
And before clicking or shift
and create your clone, your first two module,
then Ctrl D you can can create, uh, more
cloning control D
or command D basically just uh, repeats the last command
and then you can select all the row and do the same thing.
So optional alt in the keyboard,
which shift your, keep the alignment
and the points you touch.
It's totally fine
And you keep going.
I was in the X-ray mode in, uh, common y
control Y in the keyboard.
So if you want to be sure your design is here,
of course you can also, um, reverse
apply the field instead of the stroke.
You can double click on the stroke, apply a color,
white or black.
And I was saying you can also see in advance
how the models basically interlock between each other,
not for the nesting clearly.
But uh, if you want to create this kind of guidelines
that you cannot add, uh, um, to the big documentation,
you can give some, uh, transparency, some, a example 60%
and you can see how the pattern will
look like with
the same command we showed earlier.
Control, uh, shift.
We can move this one all over
and see a new design, um, appearing.
This is just for a simulation
and uh, again, you can select everything.
Um, double click or specifying.
We don't want any field to be applied to our models.
And the stroke has to be, in this case red,
RGB or green
or blue to 50 50 0 0.
And of course, if some pieces don't fit,
we can always remove them.
We can make a group control G or here at the bottom.
So now we can move our selection
and we are able to rotate it to split it
and ate our, uh, other boards.
So of course if I want another board to be ready
for cutting, I can either send the same file
or create a copy.
So clicking on the R board dimensions
and the same command press, alter option shift
and I create a second one.
Um, we have been speaking yesterday, uh, mostly about te
and uh, of course there are just three, uh, main shapes
that allows you really to escalate a shape on the board.
As you can see here, especially if you reverse this
election, um,
the board is as some waste.
When you have shapes like circles, you have, um, a choice.
For example, you can, uh, decide to use the space in
between, uh, creating a new model.
So for example, creating, um,
different connections.
So applying either an illustrator
or so on fusion, um, the same slots.
So this piece also becomes part of a pattern
Or try to expand, for example, the shape.
Um, yeah. So let's continue.
Let's go back to our red. Um, zero zero.
Uh, we're always able to also dimension the board.
We have,
let's say this is our final.
So we select everything Control a common A,
we put back 0.01 millimeters or airline.
And um, we're basically done for laser cutting.
We can generate our first modules.
Of course, the first step would be always, um, to test
a couple of them first before sending, um, the full sheet.
And the workflow is the same.
You can just save it as um,
PDF,
S-P-G-A-P-S, all of them are vector format.
And you can keep the default settings.
And when you're done, you should be able to see
the moment you zoom, your file is ready.
Uh, I would like to move to Rhino.
So if you have some questions about Illustrator,
you can also unmute yourself.
Now
you can stop share for one second
and can gimme some feedback if it's too slow,
if it's too fast,
if something is not clear.
I dunno the level of everyone.
I think that everything is good.
And, uh, the explanation is very clear.
The thing that we need to, uh,
practice this like work on our own, uh, files
to make our own files.
And, uh, in this case, maybe we'll have more questions.
Okay, so we can move to Rhino.
We see different approach
and we try another pattern, which is more,
makes more sense for the sation.
That is gonna be based on a square.
So was trying to do
and do, this ones
exactly the module source.
So good exercise, if you have this kind of configurations
and modules in your is for example, understand how, uh,
the big piece is made, try to deconstruct them, try to, uh,
create again this one with scissors and paper
and try to create different patterns
that also could use this locking
systems as the ones that you have.
Or try to understand how a pattern
that is being generated also from an image can be, um,
through a series of shapes, lines can be created again,
uh, and vectorized.
So let's start simple again. And we can do this one.
And again, here we have a female
and a male as slightly different than the previous one.
But still, uh, we can identify
that follows the same exact approach.
These are the male parts.
And of course, for example, there are multiple ways.
Even though you have just four slots, the moment you start,
uh, adding slots, you have way multiple, uh,
way more ways also to, uh, interlock your modules.
Uh, if you want to go 3D usually the way is
to stack the pieces on top of each other.
So also this way you can just insert this kind of arrows
inside and you have a module that is a little bit more 3D.
But in this case, since you're using the first lot, uh,
ready for the interlocking of this module, you can
have way more here to be used
to grow this.
Uh, and if you have this kind of modules, uh,
becoming 3D, uh, since uh, felt something very thin
and foldable, you can always think
of adding something inside.
Like, uh, when not shall we, maybe you have the,
the sample we did in Armenia,
we were actually putting wool inside.
So we had something that was really, um, popping out.
Yeah, what is the thickness of your pieces?
No, this is, uh, around two millimeters.
It hold very well the connection,
especially if it's not very small.
Uh, the other piece I have here is also very nice
and this is, uh, uh, velvet.
And the one I had
before, uh, was actually used to construct a bag.
So there was a bigger piece that was actually,
um, versatile.
So was becoming 3D.
You can use it in multiple ways
or so forth, a shoulder piece.
So again, there are many modules that are able to, um,
develop into the third dimension.
Uh, let's go back to rhino.
'cause we have still a couple of things to do.
Uh, so the moment you launch Rhino, uh, we can do it again.
We can open, sorry,
I raise my hand, but I think you can't see me,
therefore I interrupt you.
I'm really sorry. Uh,
I have a question about the, uh, pieces.
You know, uh, based on what we are thinking about the, uh,
circular fashion, maybe we need to use waste materials
or, uh, I don't know any other materials which is not,
uh, completely like, uh, the new one or raw materials.
Therefore, uh, if we want to, uh, obey these rules that, uh,
we, uh, made a special, uh, cut for each material,
maybe we couldn't, uh, manage it.
Because if we want to use, uh, waste materials,
maybe we don't have any enough, uh,
materials in a special dimension
or even, uh, you know, uh, to be honest,
I it seems it is not really a circular, you know, I mean,
uh, it seems you, uh, for example, you use a velvet fabric,
which is totally not waste
and, uh, try to cut it in a special models, you know,
to be honest, it is in conflict with the approach of, uh,
recycling, you know, or circular fashion
because, um, in my, uh, mind I think we need
to use waste materials
or, um, you know, some materials which is not usable in our,
um, you know, routines.
Yeah, yeah. What you say Pedro?
And, uh, what we have been saying that prototyping is, uh,
pretty se very unsustainable.
This is still a learning process.
Uh, they were saying also yesterday,
whatever works on textile works on paper,
paper is at least a hundred percent recyclable.
We also have recipes for creating your own paper.
So, uh, you can use any material you have at your hand
and, um, maybe starting with small pieces,
the small pieces can be cut and, um,
and most of the materials are no.
So if you have scraps, you can try to identify
to measure the idea you have of the materials.
So either if you have 20 centimeter might be enough
for you to create a module.
You know, I need to know, uh, if it is mandatory to, uh,
cut it with laser cutter or something like this.
Because for example, I'm thinking about the, um,
filter cigarette filters.
You know, it is not possible for, uh, I don't know,
laser cutting or something like this,
but it is possible for using in, uh, recycling.
Therefore, I ask this question, I need to know, uh, some
of these rules is mandatory for us or not.
We can do our, um, create,
use our creativity in this way.
Um, maybe you can save this idea for later,
for other weeks, but yes, the week focuses on
the use of the laser cut.
So it's, uh, kind of mandatory to use the, the laser, thank
You, thank, but Against using, uh,
or it's impossible for you to get, uh, some materials.
Uh, you can always, you know, um, even if you buy some felt,
you can reuse the felt also in many other weeks
for other things or drying the paper as well.
Um, yeah, and really they,
um, recycle it.
Yeah, yeah. Good.
No worries about that. You're, you're learning.
So, uh, whatever is, is needed to learn.
Mm-Hmm. It's not a waste. Okay.
Okay. Thank you very much. Thank you for
Explanation out of this, the,
we have a weak Texas scaffold
where you can use different layers that you use
for the learning process and then combine them with the rein
and create, um, hard objects instead of soft, okay?
You're going have plenty of ideas
to recycle all the different assignments you'll be
creating in the six months.
Okay, Thank you. Thank you very much. No problem. Uh,
Sorry, can I add something?
Um, because sometimes we use also the leftovers,
and to have this small pieces, it gives you the possibility
to really use those leftovers
and there so you can scale your, um,
your parts so you, it can fit, uh, your leftover,
for example, the leftover of the leather of different,
uh, textiles.
Yeah. You know, the moment you have a, a vector file,
you can just select everything
and scale down of course.
So just, uh, be sure that you are measuring
also the, um, your slot.
An illustrator is a bit tricky,
but you can always either with the rules
or double clicking on the segment.
And here, there an icon says transform.
You can actually inspect, um, the dimensions of your line.
So of course also illustrator, um, can handle some, uh,
okay, let's move to Rhino.
And
So This is Rhino eight.
I'm on a Mac. It might be a little bit different.
The interface compared to windows, uh, the commands do, uh,
are the same, um, at the very beginning.
Um, maybe when you create it
and you open it again, it ask you, um, to make a selection
between, uh, different canvases.
Uh, always be sure to, uh, select the one
for millimeters, more objects.
Um, so similar comes with a fusion,
and here is the interface.
So you have, uh, now we can close.
Usually you have a palette for the layers on the,
uh, right, you have this kind of four views where
that are clickable.
That means you can enter
and enlarge, um, the different, uh,
top front right and perspective.
You have agreed with the axis similar again
to fusion so early.
And we have the commands
that in this time are here on the side.
Uh, very important thing to do at the beginning is
to enable the snaps.
These, uh, os snaps, uh, palette you see here down.
Usually it's good to keep end meet center
and intersection so you can identify different points in
your modules, in your design.
This is also valid for the 3D modeling.
Uh, you have different options.
Um, we're gonna handle the vector, so we'll not, uh, go,
um, into the 3D now.
Um, so, uh, what we did
before for fusion is starting with the top view.
Uh, here again, you can see, uh, actually a very small, um,
a good advice is also to enable the, um, the gumble.
So you can, uh, move, for example, uh,
your pieces on the grid, uh, in a very intuitive way.
You have a common line in Rhino,
and here you can write, uh, commands
that might sound familiar to you,
but all of you had at least, uh, some experience
during the past week in Rhino.
So, you know, some move a little bit forward.
Um, if a command, um,
is not also enabled in the interface, you can search here,
for example, the gumball
Ramon.
That doesn't come for me.
Usually it should see, uh, to sit here
and, uh, in a different way, uh, compared to field.
And if you look at here at the bottom,
if you are on windows, it may be, uh, somewhere else
you can, uh, this pressed.
So record is three.
This doesn't mean that you can go back
and modify the things you did earlier,
but you can see the different commands that you selected.
Um, so double click also
to exit the view and see in the perspective,
visit the front, see the right, what you're making.
For this week, we're gonna just work at the top.
So you can just ignore the front
and right gonna be just a simple line.
So to begin with, we said we are trying to do, uh,
these two models here
and see how RiNo this can be done in dry.
Um, again, you have options for polygons.
So for example, you can start clicking on rectangle.
And here again, you can choose between the one
that starts from the center
or the one start from two different points.
Um, I usually start with the one that goes in the center.
It doesn't really matter. And again, you are asked
to specify the center of your model of your polygon.
You can, um, write the dimension
or directly the, the coordinates.
Um, for example, if I want this to be in the center
of my grid, I can just write zero, command zero,
and I'm gonna have this one placed at the center
of the access I see here on the top.
So I just click one time,
and now I can put, um, for example, I can click
for the second, uh, point the things
that the rhino works in a different way of fusion.
So you may need to scale down, scale up again.
Um, your rectangle.
A common way when we use polygon is actually, um,
you can always cancel.
Also clicking on the commands back on the panel is to use,
uh, not from the center,
but to click the rectangle from point to point.
And this way you can give a dimension.
Uh, Claudia, sorry for interruption.
I think we see a screen on top of the, uh, screen
that you're using using in Rhino, because Yeah.
Yeah, that's perfect.
Ah, you didn't see this one?
No, not this one. We saw another rhino screen
that wasn't moving around.
Ah, I'm so sorry. Okay.
I was just saying thank you, Ashley, that, uh,
you have different options to choose, um,
between all the shapes, different polygons.
If you want a polygon to start from the corner,
you can just select and insert the coordinates.
0.0 goes, uh, from top of, at the center of the axis,
you can release to create your circle.
Uh, here's the, is the gamble enabled,
and um, also to identify, uh,
what's the size You have, um, many ways to debug it.
You can write distance,
specify the two point
and understand, uh, for me it's written on top,
but this is five point, uh, five millimeters,
or again, come through Z
and you can enable this icon for line, uh, linear dimension.
And you can understand here how big is your design.
And this, uh, the same comes to the fusion.
Uh, they do not have an impact on the, on the file,
but the ran, you need to delete them
before exporting the itself.
So, um, I would instead choosing the rectangle
or the square from two different point
and just click randomly on the grid, my first point,
and assigning the dimension
for the height and for the width.
So, uh, let's keep this consistent as
before, let's say 50, uh, millimeter by 50.
So 50, and you can see already that this is locked.
And then 50, um, sorry, enter
to, um, or tab to confirm selection.
And then 50 again,
you can click here on the line of dimension
and see that actually this is 50.
Okay, so we have our first, uh, square.
We can say again, uh,
this time we can actually start with the male part
before we started with the females.
So how to recreate this one?
Uh, let's try another way.
So I, before we did with the lines,
now we can use a polygon, for example, we see
that this is kind of a square, inside the square.
So, um, we can take
the square from the center, for example.
And since you have the snaps enabled, you can,
the moment you move closely with the mouse, you're able
to identify the center of your shape.
So you click
and, uh, for example, you specify, um, an initial number.
It's a square, so, uh,
it's gonna be a little bit smaller.
So probably
45 by 45.
This way we see, uh, we basically created, uh,
an offset of a circle.
Uh, probably it's too big to be, um, rotated.
We can only, uh, scale it down, scale it up.
Um, we could also do the same thing
with the offset command.
Um, doesn't really matter,
and I know you can scale everything and down and up.
You have many references also in the square.
So for example, we can just rotate it 45
degrees from the center.
And to do so, you can either write a command, rotate,
or just drag this, uh, blue icon
Rotate.
And again, is to specify the center of your rotation.
All right? Um,
And either, uh, plus 45, minus 45,
or, uh, by hand you have the midpoint enabled in the snap,
so it can always, uh, referred to them.
So this is how your design should look like.
We don't really, I need to know, uh, we have the references
of the edges of the square, so it doesn't really matter
how big it is, one
'cause we can just scale it up, scale it down.
So we can use the command, scale,
scale or scale to D
and we can say, uh, we can specify a point.
So for example, the center to the end
of the point, and then click in.
So be sure to have this one highlighted enabled.
Otherwise, it might be not easy for you to spot exactly
the intersection between the different squares.
So what we created now is this
square, inside the square 45 degrees.
And, uh, we can try to replicate
what is here in the pattern.
For example, uh, cutting three minutes online to have this,
uh, male, four male parts, uh, generated.
So again, we have plenty of commands here.
What we can do as we're saying early, is to, for example,
create an offset off.
Offset is like, um, a copy.
You find the command, um, here also between, uh, the palette
or just write offset.
And you need to specify this three millimeters,
if you want the offset to be outside or inside.
So a copy of your square scaled down or scaled up.
Uh, and using, for example, five millimeters, maybe you can
write a little bit more.
And, uh, you need to use, uh, plus
and minus for the direction.
So whatever is inside a minus five,
for example, sorry, I'll do it again.
Minus five is gonna be placed, uh,
inside the second square.
And also, as you can see in the preview, if you are inside
with your pointer
or outside, you can specify the direction.
So let's say this one.
Uh, when you go inside, I write six, so it's gonna be, um,
minus six millimeters.
And this is my new square.
If it's confusing this way, uh, you can only say that, uh,
this line is my reference shape, so I want it to be red.
I'm gonna move it on this layer.
So I select the square, I click on layer one, and I write,
and I do change object layer.
This way, um, I can see clearly, uh, let's say my shape,
and now I'm gonna work on this line to create this.
So I can use the command trim.
If I don't see where the scissors are,
I can just click on trim
and basically, um, read, um, I read
select the cutting objects.
So the objects I need to split
to cut my, the, the lines I want to keep.
So in this case, um,
I want to trim the, these lines, these four lines inside.
So I can use this square as a cutting object.
So I say I confirm the selection
and I delete
This lines inside.
Um, I'm gonna do the opposite here, just
to keep this kind of arrow.
And I can do, again, I can press the space bar like fusion
to repeat the latest command
and specify that this in this, uh, this way,
the cutting object will be this,
uh, four lines.
And the objects, the lines that I want to trim will be
this ones when I'm,
I click done when I'm happy with the result.
And again, I can select all the lines that I want to keep
and move them onto the red layer.
So change object layer.
And if I don't need the rest, I can just the whole shift,
select the four of them and to remove them
or trim them again.
Okay, so this is my module
from here to here.
Well, I was not precise.
This is six millimeters, this is 50 millimeters,
and this is all I need to know.
So we can create, for example, the female part,
and again, we can use the similar technique that we did,
uh, before infusion.
So we can select this one
and, uh, copy
for one point to another.
If you hold shift, you move on to the same direction.
And, uh, select enter.
If you want to move your second design,
second module onto another layer,
you can just select all the lines you want to appear.
For example, layer number three and say change object.
Uh, double click. You can change the color.
Always be sure the colors are l, g, B.
And we can do like we did earlier,
so we can construct the lines that are in between.
For example, we can use the line
to one point to another.
And also, again, here we have different commands to do so.
So for example, we have this icon for array.
If you click on the arrow here, it can actually expand it
and move it anywhere you want.
It can decide if you want to have a rectangular array
or a polar array, something that
takes a center as a reference.
Okay, so I'll do it again. This is just to save time.
It is not gonna apply any relationships like fusion,
so you're not able later on to modify the selection
and iterate, for example, the numbers.
So I click on the polar array
because I have a center that I can use.
If I don't see the center appearing, I need
to move a little bit further until I see the center.
If I have too many snaps enabled here,
I might not able to see it at all.
So always be sure, uh, center is enabled.
And then you can always click the others.
Then the number of item you want to, patterns gonna be four.
And then, uh, the angle is gonna be 360 degrees.
So they go all over the circle
and you can click done and confirm.
And you have your four lines that of course, you can select,
uh, together with the other shape, move to, um, the layer,
keeping the selection and say, I want this to be a group.
You have two icons here.
One for group objects, one for ungroup, and the shortcut
and the keyboard is the same.
Ctrl G command, command, G and C shift G to ungroup.
You can select, uh, remove the other lines.
And here is your email, this group.
So you can actually able to move it anywhere
or specify the distance here
or holding shift and move it wherever you want.
This is just reference, you can always delete them.
And, um, to do the nest thing, actually, if you really want
to move it, uh, it's much better if you select the option
to move and you specify from point to point.
If you just go to the laser now
and you print this one out, um, it's not,
let's say it is not actually totally correct
because you're gonna have a double line.
So you can always, uh, for example, ungroup,
um, this one, the second that we grouped earlier.
And you can trim the line just to say, for example,
time, in this case you have only two,
but think the moment you're gonna have a hundred pieces
is also time added to the laser cutter for nothing,
and is a double line.
Even the, even though we, I are dealing with a very small
resolution, and the line is gonna be point, uh,
zero, one millimeter still is one line added to your design,
one more passes over.
So also consider it is the moment you're doing a nesting.
And, uh, you can always write trim and trim the line.
Or, um, another way very convenient in Rhino, for example,
is actually this one to explode.
Uh, and on windows, you see this one on top, on the Mac,
you find the command happening here at the bottom.
So it says that the curve has been
exploded into four segment.
So now these segments are totally clickable.
You can get rid of one of the lines
and for example, select the three back and join them.
Also, remember to join the loops in, uh, in Rhino
because, uh, again, um,
the laser gonna, I'm not gonna do this line, for example,
altogether, that's gonna stop from one point to another
before starting again with the second line.
And of course, uh, these are gonna be cut in the laser,
so you want to move them onto the same layer.
So again, right click onto the panel here
and change object layer.
You can move them around.
Of course, you can scale your design scale
if you need to do so.
The, or you can specify a factor.
Uh, you can also testate a plan here.
Um, good, uh, practices to create.
For example, here, the area you can specify with a square,
uh, for example, the bed of your laser or in the materials.
For example, if you have one meter of your textile by, um,
50 centimeters,
you can actually rename it
and you can bring your models inside your space.
You can also, uh, hide some element where you have the icon
and show elements again.
So if you're now the selection is bothering, uh,
your design process, you can always close them
and you can proceed to, uh, like we did in Illustrator,
you can do the semi rhino.
So you can deselect a full board.
Um, you can select both of the shape you want
to pattern and click back in this array,
or from here where we put it earlier.
So click on the first one.
It's uh, a text studies a rectangular.
So it doesn't make sense that we use the polar array.
I'm gonna use the, uh, rectangular array,
and we specify the number in the X or the Y direction.
So for example, um, if you're good with math,
you already know how many of them, you know,
to test select fully your board, or you can just guess.
And then split the different modules into different boards.
For example, let's say you want 10
and you want, uh, five here,
seven here, and one in Z.
And you can space them
by clicking the first point.
And the second point, if you go closer with the mouse,
you actually, you're actually able to
control better and the space.
And when you are good with what you did, you just select.
Or if you're not, you can go back to the math here,
uh, and change the number.
So press enter when you're done,
and this is how your modules, uh, will look like.
And again, if you really want to be, uh, precise,
like I said before, we just got read the one line here.
Uh, so the vertical is, is okay, you can just, uh,
explode the different
segments, different parts here
as since you already have the reference, you can go back
and create the lines in between until the end.
So this is the, uh, common practice
to save time, machining,
and also not to have a double line onto your modules.
Let's say this is done correctly.
Of course, you can select these modules
to not actually fit here.
So I select only the parts, uh,
I want to move, I can update them, I can reposition them
even manually or with the software, uh,
that I was mentioning yesterday, like, uh, SVG,
nest, deepness.
And, uh, you just replace your, your module.
Once you're done,
you also get rid of, uh,
your reference, your bounding box.
You select everything.
Um, be sure you are on the current,
uh, layer here.
And basically you just, um,
select, uh, this, be sure it's a continuous line.
It's gonna be cut. And, uh, it's either you specify
with 0.01, uh, millimeters, the resolution of the, uh,
stroke for laser cutting,
or you select line
And then you just proceed to save, export.
Export selected. Yes.
And, uh, I recently upgraded the version of dryness, um,
and finished my license days, so I cannot do that.
But you can do it and import it in Illustrator
or Inscape or just, uh, straight to the laser.
You can just do cont repeat if your laptop is connected
to the laser, and you can find your, um,
laser software here in the destination.
Always be sure you are working.
Uh, in this case, we have been using millimeters, so
also the options for the scale, uh, remain the same.
Okay, so a bit, let me close the window.
Okay, if you have any s
otherwise, I have a couple of more things that I wanted
to show you about data installation.
So how we can actually, uh, play with Symmetries to create,
uh, patterns and modules.
So I'm going back to Illustrator,
gonna share my screen,
and, uh, we can see here, uh, this case,
I'm gonna need some access.
I'm gonna put back my rules Control R
or from View Display Rules.
And, um, as you can see yesterday, there are many ways
to, um, create a selections between patterns.
They all follow basically three principles
that are either a translation
or a rotational, or reflections.
Uh, doesn't exist. I, I believe kids do in school.
Um, it's a, something very playful that you can
actually achieve by playing with papers, uh,
colors and C source.
We can use some polygons in the digital world here.
So we can have, for example, um,
a square with an illustrator.
You can just select the polygon, click
and specify the number.
Uh, we don't really care of the numbers now.
We are just, uh, playing with shapes.
Of course, you want to assign a number.
You can do that even later.
The moment you select the shape you go to transform.
And then you can say, actually when it to be 45,
um, you can use, uh, you can create an access,
what like we did with fusion, with lines.
So you can just drag in the center
your axis from top.
And again, if you do not see them, there are under views,
view and, uh, rule.
And, um, we can try to create, uh,
a shape using the first principle of translation
that basically says whatever happens here at the top happens
in the opposite way at the bottom and vice versa.
Uh, so for example, we can add shapes, uh,
we can sub supplied shapes.
We can, uh, also as four shapes.
I'd say we want to, um, use a triangle.
There's this polygon tool.
Again, you click, you specify the number,
or both sides say one,
three, I.
If I click V on the keyboard, I go back to the pointer.
I can only scale down.
Of course, this can also be done in Fusional or Rhino.
Uh, if the feel is bothering me, I can just, uh,
put the color double click to change the color.
I can position my shape, um, wherever I want.
Um, this way we're gonna use the Pathfinder commands
to combine shapes together, subtract, uh,
do this kind of operations.
You mostly done also last week about the bullions.
So if you do not see this one here,
you can find again, I believe.
Uh, and the window
or view, I believe view, uh, window.
So yeah, here it is, sabbatical order.
So be sure you have the pathfinder enabled.
And for example, you can, um, even click in the vertex,
move the shape, uh, here,
or you can example, um,
selecting here, the second tool.
And this way you can manipulate
directly the vertex of your polygon.
You can also add a point.
We have, uh, many command to do that. One is the pan.
If you click, uh, with the pan onto the edge of the polygon,
you're able to add new points.
Then you can use to manipulate the shape again.
You take the second option, second tool,
and you create something else.
Uh, you can also split, uh, with the pathfinder mode,
your shape, uh, using the lines
I believe, and also split, um, with a command cut
and basically correspond to this one, to the scissors.
So we can also split our model, our path,
and we see that now, uh, the first part can be detached.
Um, we can see
and play, uh, with the shape we have now.
So for example, um, go back to one.
Yeah, so I can place this one,
um, wherever I want.
I just have to be sure I can place it also.
And I can use the same command that showed
before, uh, option or alt
and then shift to drag it.
So whatever happens on top will happen at the bottom.
And I can try to subtract, so select my target body
and the second, uh, shape I have it.
So this one, um, it's removed from top,
but it is added at the same time.
It's either illustrated, you avoid coincidence
or you are very precise
and you add from the bottom.
So this way it's uh, your shape is kind of already selected.
So we, uh, we did an operation on top
of your square in this case,
and we reflect the same at the bottom.
So if you take it up
and pattern it, you see that it's perfectly escalated.
Of course, you can also manipulate it if you are more
into organic shapes.
There is this kind of, uh, icons.
The moment you select command or control
and you can apply a fillet edge to, uh,
to the perimeter, the edge.
And again, you, we can do the same thing.
So as you said, we have this axis.
So whatever happens on one side happens on the other
one in the opposite way.
Um, you can have, uh, of course another shape.
So ellipse, for example, you can put it wherever you want.
We shift your, be sure it's a circle
and not on ellipse anymore.
If you zoom in and select the shape, you're actually able
to get theit point
and then you clone it.
So you click on option
Shift and you drag it
and, uh, to be sure that are on the same.
Uh, for example, you can do like we did
before, you can center align everything.
It depends on where this one to be
or not.
Uh, but it's important these two are on the same exact line.
So also you can just select, for example,
the two shapes together
and say I want them to be center line.
And then you are able to move them wherever you want.
So we're gonna, um, put the height was
before we're gonna remove from one side
and we're gonna add from the other one.
So the first icon to unite the shape,
the second one to remove.
And, uh, it's not the most meaningful shape,
but it's uh, definitely ated.
And again, we can do what we did before.
We can get rid of the axis and move the this one.
Uh, here, this is just to, to preview
how de distillation will work.
So we can select both of them until they match.
And then we can pattern this one with control D.
We take the full draw and we go down.
And here is our test related pattern.
Of course, you should start the adding colors.
So we can select alternated one by one, you know, also see
how this will look like,
or you can decide to use your module, uh, for example,
to add some interlocking.
So you may think to add some, uh,
female parts, male parts.
This is, uh, very versatile, for example, to be a male part.
And you can do the same thing in Illustrator.
You can understand how big
is the distancing between, uh, two parts
and keep, uh, this lot consistent.
Also for a male part, you can run a simulation to see
how this will interlock in the
module, uh, and so on.
So you can always use also your tes related, uh, design
as a base for further, uh, for the creation of the modules.
And of course, this shape is not, uh, very beautiful.
But you can start, for example, from, um, from map
and tries to, uh, like, uh, Asher was doing in,
uh, in his paintings.
Try to reconstruct them with polygons and with interlocking.
So this is a way, uh, to do this with, um, transition.
We can see example, take another report
and can see how distillation can also be applied,
uh, rotational symmetries.
So something very similar.
Uh, again, you can start from a polygon.
Doesn't matter which one.
Uh, yeah, we can start with the triangle.
This time you can always use a square.
And it's always best if you drag
and drop your axis just as a reference.
Don't really need this one.
But, uh, they are symmetry X, yes.
And uh, here you need to use, uh, protection. Again.
Also it works. Uh, if you have a square,
we can use another tool.
For example, we can use the, the pan.
We can try maybe to create an arc here, something
that can be like a wave and repeat it.
Something very simple. So you can select the pan.
Click on one point, on the first point on the second point.
And the third point until the axis.
Either enter or click on the pointer
to confirm the selection.
Uh, you can always manipulate this one.
Uh, with the second tool here
that you have the direct selection, you can apply a fill it.
Okay, Let's see.
We like it. Or you can click on the point.
You can actually move it.
Uh, when you're happy with the results, uh,
we can continue.
We can um, rotate it, not measure it.
We want this one to be here down.
Um, to do this in Illustrator, you can do it right click.
It's much better to do it on the keyboard.
So for example, if you have this line selected, you press
R for rotation.
And you see that there is a small icon here in light blow.
Uh, this is identifies the center of your shape.
And you want to be sure this one is exactly
here in the midpoint.
So you can try to move it.
I'll do it again. So first you have rotation
and then you need to select with option
or alt the
center of your rotation.
So I click the line that I want to rotate.
I click on R rotate in,
or this command that you can see here.
Again, I click here, I click on rotate shortcut R,
and then I want this point to be moved here.
So on the keyboard, the select option
or alt depends if the rear are on windows or a Mac
and specify the point here.
And then I want this to be minus 180.
So it goes exactly down
before confirming, okay, I want this to be a copy.
So, So my line is duplicated
and I select both of them.
I want them to join like in, uh, RH orl J.
So now all this is only one line
and um, you can actually already imagining
how my um, shape is coming.
So once I created this, I selected
and I continued creating a rotational as symmetry.
So again, I press R or rotate.
My point in this case is to be, um, one
of the verts of the triangle.
So I can say here with the alt
or option, I click here one time
and immediately this popup comes
and this has to be, uh, 60 degrees as a triangle is.
So I'm gonna copy this one and then do the same.
So option or alt click.
And again, 60 degrees a copy.
So now what I have is a shape made of this
lines that I can join.
And again, they're not very beautiful.
Very better that I can use, uh, for the selection.
So now that I have this one, I can again rotate it.
So rotate it, optional alt my point.
And here I'm gonna create a copy.
Something went wrong, so I don't really match perfectly.
Uh, but here's this, the concept is this one.
So I can specify under color
and then continue replicate
and create rotation asymmetries between all of them
or just, uh, move them
At the moment.
Also, you have a preview. You can specify, you can see
where actually your design is gonna be placed.
Or of course you can select both of them and do it manually.
They all end up fully isolated anyway.
Again, you can use them as a base for your design.
So you can remove the field, you can set everything
and use the red and you can add some
interlocking to the module.
I think they just don't match.
'cause they, I was not very precise. Yeah,
where your point should be exactly on the vertex here
and exactly in the middle here.
Rotate.
Yeah, no, it's much better.
And then again, rotate everything.
And every time you choose a different center,
I'm gonna have, uh, this repetition growing, uh, forever.
Yeah. And um,
yeah, we can just uh, uh,
move the last 10 minutes on Inscape.
I dunno if you have quite any questions about it.
Of course, this is not mandatory to use.
It's, uh, the software also allows you
to play in this direction.
So it's always, uh, good to give it a shot.
Uh, let me screen share again. Should be able to
See. Sorry, Claudia,
can I ask a question
before we go to the next scale?
Yeah. About the alignments, uh,
that showed there.
Uh, I was wondering if we can align using just the vertical
lines and horizontal lines
or we can use the different, uh, lines to align
underneath or shapes.
Um, I mean, for example, uh, I,
you remember the game from my other,
so we have the game from, uh, our childhood.
We were making the patterns like this.
When you fold the paper in different, uh,
access with different access and you cut them and
after you open them and you have Yeah.
And get, and we have, you have differentiate.
So I was wondering if it's possible
to make using the administrator in the same logic
that you showed, showed already?
Yeah. 'cause during this time
Fold it. Now
We can have some Yeah, but
You see, you fold it in four is actually,
Yeah, some parts in four, some parts in like in more
parts it's the same, but yeah.
Reputation. Yeah. Yeah,
Not right.
So I can use the same logic to make this symmetry,
to align the, to have different shapes in the same line.
Yes, you just need to add the interlocking.
And if of course, if you find, uh, some shapes that, uh,
I know in Armina you have
so much heritage that you can explore.
Like we did in the boot camp.
Uh, couple
of girls were reflecting on the pattern they saw in,
in the churches and they were trying to, uh,
digitalize this, um, heritage in order not
to be lost. And
It was, yes. And also
the wraps.
Yeah, the wrap and mostly pictures in German.
Yeah, architecture is a great explanation for this week.
Uh, yeah, I go back to screen share very quickly.
And what just I wanted to show you is
that all this is actually about to do it also in Inscape,
you don't have to, uh, by illustrator,
you can digitalize a picture.
For example, we can take, if I copy
and paste it, even though it's vector, uh, Inscape,
I don't think recognize it as a vector,
but uh, looks like an image.
So I just copy paste it inside.
But I'm actually able to probably trace bit map
and as you can see here in the panel,
and transform this one into a vector.
Yeah. So this is the copy and this is my vector. Perfect.
I just copy paste it. I want this to be vector.
I should have exported from illustrator into SVG,
for example, and then loaded back in the softwares VSVG.
Um, just a shortcut, since the shape is very simple,
is perfectly recognized now as a, as a vector.
And that means that you can scale it, you can modify it.
So the people that are more familiar with Inscape also,
this is an option.
And uh, here there is just a very nice command
that allows you to clone the shape
and create this kind of tile.
So the command is clone, create tile clones,
and you can select a different symmetry to be applied with.
So there are so many, for example, uh,
translation in this case.
And then you can specify the, uh, rows
and columns and see the preview.
The nice thing when you clon the Inscape is that, uh, all
of the, um, shapes are linked between each other.
So what, what happens
to the first one will happen
automatically towards the others.
Mm-Hmm. Including the colors.
So for example, this, this one back, uh, the feel,
no, okay, it's not probably fully recognized
as a, as a vector.
I should have saved as vector imported later.
Uh, but this is the concept. So you have, uh, your shape
Or it comes, uh, with fill it.
Okay? So your square,
and again, you are able to, uh, clone it from edit it,
clone and create the tiles.
And of course you can specify more
and create your, uh, the isolated button.
So whatever happens, usually the first one is a copy.
You can get rid of this one
because what matters is the first.
So whatever happens here happens also there.
And here I only have four points specified scale
and this for the fill it.
But of course, if you have a polygon
with more points since the beginning specified,
you're actually able to, um, to be consistent
and create this kind of pattern all at once.
Maybe with the stars,
No more points.
And then again, added clone, tile, Crohns
and any of the symmetry actually will work with the star.
And uh, of course you can space them very close
and get rid of the first one.
And with the second option, probably you should be able
to modify the polygon.
Yeah.
So you can really have fun with, uh, this very simple tool.
And then again, in INCAP post, you can select everything,
uh, remove the feel, go to the stroke paint
and add 2 55, 55, uh, LGB
and airline or laser cutting.
And when you're done, you can select everything
and either print or export
or save us 3G PD, F, and Excel.
Any questions,
try to use all the software together.
It's um, it's gonna be very powerful.
And um, yeah, if you want, I can give you the working files,
also the, where I did Infu in, um, uh,
an illustrator and the pattern I have in Infusion.
So if you want to go back and see how it was made
or the vector file, uh, you can go back.
I can, I'll put it in Matmos
and uh, yeah, let me know.
Remember to tag us if you need some help in Matmos.
If you have, uh, if you need some
support, you have questions.
Otherwise I kept you here for two hours.
Um, I'll go to the lab.
Okay then see you in Matmos. Happy exploration.
Looking forward to seeing your
beautiful creations next week.
Thank you Claudia. Thank you.
It was very interesting. Bye everyone for printing.
Save your vector files for extruding them later.
Bye everyone.